一千万卢比支付给了尊敬的纳拉辛哈·拉奥
Money, rupees one crore was paid to honourable P.V. Narasimha Rao...
印度总理
...the Prime Minister of India.
他只是在兜售谎言，就像他一直做的那样..
He's just selling lies, as he has always done...
把媒体的注意力从骗局转移到首相身上
...to divert the media's attention from the scam to the Prime Minister.
这不是“哈尔沙德 · 梅塔骗局” ，而是“ p.v. 纳拉辛哈 · 拉奥骗局”
It is not the 'Harshad Mehta scam'. It is the 'P.V. Narasimha Rao scam'.
如果双方继续发表声明，可能很快就会出问题
And if both sides keep giving statements, problems may arise.
[苏切塔]“即使哈沙德在撒谎，他也在诋毁当权者的形象... ... ”
[Sucheta] 'Even if Harshad was lying, he was denting the image of those in power...'
“ ... 每个人都知道有必要解决这个问题”
'...and everyone was aware that a solution was necessary.'
梅塔先生，你说你有一张去首相官邸访客证
Mr. Mehta, you said, that you have a visiting slip...
... 日期是11月4日
...dated 4th November, for the Prime Minister's residence.
是的，没错
Yes. That is right.
但是我找不到那张纸条
But I can't find that slip.
如果你自相矛盾..
[Das] If you contradict yourself...
就没有任何理由反对首相
...you don't really have any case against the Prime Minister.
“我希望你能理解”
[Das] 'I hope you understand.'
奇怪的是，哈沙德开始自相矛盾
[Sucheta] 'Curiously, Harshad began to contradict himself.'
他对首相的指控永远无法得到证实... ..
'His claims and accusations against the Prime Minister could never be proven...'
他说，哈沙德是不是想把让首相下台作为交易的一部分? 没人知道
'Was Harshad trying to let off the PM as part of a deal? Nobody knows.'
“但事情最终以失败告终，哈尔沙德也从未因贩卖毒品而被起诉”
'But the matter fizzled out. Harshad was never charged for dealing in narcotics.'
但现在，哈沙德被禁止进入股市... ..
'But now, Harshad was banned from the stock market...'
... 市场继续暴跌
'...and the market continued its free-fall.'
Sensex 指数从1992年4月的4461点开始下跌... ..
'The Sensex dropped from 4461 in April 1992...'
跌到2000点
'...to 2000.'
那些在市场崩盘中失去一切的人... ..
'Those who had lost everything in the market crash...'
“对他们来说... ... 哈沙德 · 梅塔真的是个骗子... ... ”
'...for them... Harshad Mehta was really a liar...'
已经通知了警方
The police have been informed.
你只需要在这里签字
You just need to sign here.
他为什么在这里？
Why is he here?
让他离开
Ask him to leave.
这是怎么发生的？
How did this happen?
(拉希尔的妻子)“为什么会发生这样的事? ”
[Rahil's wife] 'How did it happen?'
我不知道
I don't know.
你不知道？
You don't know?
你什么都知道
You knew everything.
(拉希尔的妻子)“你是最聪明的，不是吗? ”
[Rahil's wife] 'You were the smartest, weren't you?'
我男人
This man...
他什么都不知道
...he didn't know anything.
每当我问起..
Whenever I asked...
他会说“哈沙德知道，哈沙德知道一切”
...he would say, "Harshad knows. Harshad knows everything".
告诉我哈沙德大哥
So, tell me Harshad Bhai.
是谁杀了他？
Who killed him?
在你看来，这可能像是自杀
It may look like suicide to you.
但事实是你杀了他
But the truth is, you killed him.
你毁了他
You destroyed him.
- 算了吧-你在很久以前就杀了他
- Let it be. - You had killed him a long time ago.
只是今天才办葬礼
Today is just the funeral.
听着! 他不是唯一一个
And listen! He's not the only one.
你杀过很多像他这样的人
You've killed many people like him.
我们按照你的承诺投资了
We invested money on your word.
(拉希尔的妻子)“我们信任你，而现在... ... ”
[Rahil's wife] 'We trusted you and...'
你却说你不知道？
...you say, you don't know?
你不知道什么？
What don't you know?
你不知道什么！
What do you not know!
景色不错
It's a nice view.
是的，景色很美
Yes, the view is beautiful.
你不在家的时候，一定错过了很多美景吧？
When you were away from home, you must have missed this view?
你是指我在监狱里的时候
You mean, when I was in jail.
风景是次要的，但我确实错过了我的观点
Not this view, but I did miss my point of view.
因为我的观点从未被发表出来
Because my point of view was never printed/ captured.
来吧
Come.
在我们开始之前，吃点零食吧
[Harshad] 'Have some snacks, before we start.'
中央调查局和税务部门非常喜欢我们的零食，所以..
CBI and IT are so fond of our snacks that...
有时候他们突袭我只是为了吃点零食
...sometimes they raid me just to eat some snacks.
- 我能把它放在这儿吗?-当然
- Can I keep it here? - Sure.
你们的口味相似，所以我相信你们也会喜欢的
And your taste is similar. So, I'm sure you'll like it too.
你似乎很了解我
You seem to know a lot about me.
在市场上，你必须同时关注你的朋友和敌人
In the market, you've to keep a tab on both friends and enemies.
那么，我是朋友还是敌人？
So, am I a friend or an enemy?
你最清楚不过了
You know that best.
我想你很快也会知道的
I think you'll know it soon too.
我确定
I'm sure.
- 我们可以开始了吗?-好的..
- Shall we start? - Yes...
梅塔先生你是普通人心目中的英雄
So, Mr. Mehta, you were the common man's hero.
市场上很多人都信任你
And many people in the market trusted you.
但是当你不在的时候他们失去了信任
But then, when you were away, they lost their trust...
他们失去了毕生的积蓄，有些人甚至失去了生命
...they lost their life savings, and a few of them even lost their lives.
那么，考虑到人们因为你而丧失市场信心
So, what do you feel given the losses that people faced because of you...
面临的损失，你有什么感想..
The loss of confidence in the market...
可以挽回吗？
...can it be restored?
我问你这个是因为... 如果你能回到市场..
I'm asking you this because... if you are able to return to the market...
你能解决这个危机吗？
...can you resolve this crisis?
你还有能力吗？
Are you still capable of it?
你看..
You see...
这是一个误会
There is a misunderstanding.
我没那么大能力
I am not that capable.
我真的没有
I really am not.
事实上，我想删除这个“我”部分
In fact, I want to remove this "I" part of it.
我从来没有说过我有这样的能力
I have never said that I'm so capable.
听着... ..
[Harshad] 'Look...'
我知道，很多人因为我而承受巨大的损失
'I know, many people have faced huge losses because of me.'
尽管事实上..
In spite of the fact...
我和市场下跌没有直接关系
...that I have nothing to do with the market fall directly.
我们一直有个原则..
We always had a policy...
没有人会因为我们而遭受损失
...that no one must incur a loss because of us.
任何个人和银行都不应该因为哈尔沙德 · 梅塔而受到影响
No individual and bank should suffer because of the dues...
哈尔沙德 · 梅塔而受到影响
...of Harshad Mehta.
你想让我相信这个？
You want me to believe this?
你想让我相信..
You want me to believe...
你对你给小投资者造成的损失感到内疚
...that you feel guilty for the losses you caused to small investors.
真的吗，梅塔先生？
Really, Mr. Mehta?
听着，我把我的感受告诉你了，我表达了我的内疚
Look, I told you what I feel. I expressed my guilt.
信不信由你
Believing it or not, is up to you.
我不能强迫你相信这个
I can't force you to believe this.
尽管如此，我还是希望你相信
Though, I would like you to believe.
如果是关于损失那么..
And if it's about losses, then...
我也很痛苦，不是吗？
...I am suffering too, aren't I?
只有一个办法可以尽快解决这个问题
There's only one way to resolve this matter as soon as possible.
我们将要求特别法庭
We'll request the special court...
解决所有索赔
...that we're ready to settle all the claims.
和解委员会会处理好一切的
'The settlement commission will take care of everything.'
他们有权给予豁免
And they have all the powers to grant immunity.
如果委员会
If the commission agrees...
被说服了
...gets convinced...
你所有的财产都会解冻
...all your assets will be released.
但是，梅塔先生..
'But, Mr. Mehta...'
请不要和这些财产扯上关系
...please don't get attached to these assets.
最近，特别法庭对我的财产比我对我的财产更加重视
These days, the special court is more attached to my assets than I am.
这个 CBI..
This CBI...
难道他们就没别的事可做吗？
Do they have nothing better to do?
他们又提出了一个新的指控
Now, they've slapped a new case.
[ Bhushan ]“这是起诉书”
[Bhushan] 'This is the charge sheet.'
他们只是不想让我们摆脱这些案子
They just don't want us to get out of these cases.
他们一听说和解委员会的事
As soon as they heard about the settlement commission...
就用起诉书威胁我们
...they're threatening us with charge sheets.
想让我们闭嘴
They want to silence us.
这太荒谬了
This is ridiculous enough to give fever to a donkey.
他们说和解委员会为了将来的起诉
They say, settlement commissions can grant immunity...
可以给予的豁免权
...only for future prosecutions.
[ Bhushan ]“不适用于正在审理的案件”
[Bhushan] 'Not for ongoing cases.'
毫无疑问，CBI 以独特的方式处理了我的案子
[Harshad] 'There's no doubt that CBI has handled my case in a unique manner.'
独特的方式？
Unique manner?
你觉得自己被歧视了吗？
You feel like you've been discriminated against?
是的，我受到了歧视
Yes, I have been discriminated against.
看看我的案子
Just look at my case.
就我而言，他们已经起诉了我的整个家庭
In my case, they have notified my entire family.
我以前从没见过，你可以自己看看
I have never seen that before. You can check for yourself.
现在，我没有任何资产.. ... 事实上
Today, I am left without any assets or money... virtually.
而且他们已经起诉了我很多次了
Plus, they've filed so many cases against me.
通常，每个案件都有一个报告
Usually, every case has one FIR.
但是当涉及到我的时候，他们就在每个案件中提交了7个报告
But when it comes to me, they've filed seven FIRs in every case.
(哈沙德)“看看我身后的机构数量吧”
[Harshad] 'And look at the number of agencies going behind me.'
RBI，CBI，IT，ED，JPC...
RBI, CBI, IT, ED, JPC...
所得税部门甚至提出了这样一个大案子
The Income Tax Department filed such a big case.
一千亿卢比
Ten thousand crores.
就很离谱
[Harshad] 'Isn't that ridiculous?'
但你知道我最大的罪过是什么吗？
But, you know what my biggest crime is?
我最大的罪过就是，我是哈沙德 · 梅塔
That I'm Harshad Mehta.
[哈沙德]‘你为什么老是看这些法律书? ’
[Harshad] 'Why are you rubbing your nose in these law books?'
你打算退出生意圈，成为一名律师吗
'Are you planning to quit the business and become a lawyer?'
生意？
Business?
什么生意？
What business?
兄弟，现在只有我们懂法律，才有机会
Bhai, now only we know the law, do we stand a chance.
考虑到我们的处境..
Because, given our situation...
如果不成为律师，我们就不能做生意了
...if we don't become lawyers, we won't be able to do business.
[阿什温]“我们要为 CBI 的案子辩护”
[Ashwin] 'We have the CBI cases to defend.'
税务部门一次又一次的处罚，我们都要辩护
IT department is slapping penalty after penalty. We've to defend that.
还有我们的保管人
And our custodian...
他的数学真是一塌糊涂
[Ashwin] 'His math is all over the place.'
他的办公室连账都算不明白
'His office has not even done the accounting correctly.'
布尚说，他们低估了我们所有的资产
Bhushan was saying, they've undervalued all our assets.
该死的白痴
Bloody idiots.
“让保管人做他想做的事吧”
[Harshad] 'Let the custodian do what he wishes.'
让他来设定价值
Let him set the values.
托管人本身是没有价值的
The custodian is value-less himself.
你知道我怎么想的吗？
You know what I think?
现在是开始尝试新业务的正确时机
This is the right time to start something new.
继续
Go ahead.
开始一些新的事情
Start something new.
但这一次，问题不仅仅是我们的资产或金钱
But this time, it's not just a matter of our assets or of money.
我们的名声岌岌可危，哈沙德
Our name is at stake, Harshad.
当“纳胡”变得富有，人们开始叫他“纳萨拉”
When 'Nathhu' gets rich, people start calling him 'Nathalal'.
一旦我们有了钱，名声就会随之而来
Once we have money, the name will follow.
这不是获取名声的方式了
That's not how you build a name.
人们叫我们小偷
People are calling us thieves.
所有这些案子... 我们必须全力以赴
All these cases... we have to fight against them all.
我们必须与体制作斗争
We have to fight against the system.
我们必须洗清所有这些案子的嫌疑
We'll have to clear our names from all these cases.
否则..
Or else...
人们甚至不会放过我们的孩子
Forget us, people won't even leave our children in peace.
你觉得..
So, do you think...
你可以读几本书，几天后成为一名律师？
...you'll read a few books, and become a lawyer in a couple of days?
你认为这些案子过几天就会结束吗？
Do you think, all these cases will be over in a couple of days?
我可以问你一些非正式的问题吗？
Can I ask you something off the records?
已经三四年了... 我还在想..
It's been three to four years... and I still wonder...
到底是谁走漏了风声？
...who got this verbal diarrhoea?
[哈沙德]“你这个消息来源是谁? ”
[Harshad] 'Who turned this into a story? Who is this source?'
我从不透露我的消息来源，我认为这是不道德的
I never reveal my sources. I think it's unethical.
当然，我明白
Of course. I understand.
但是现在这件事已经过去这么久了，又有什么关系呢？
But now this matter is old, it's stale. How does it matter?
那又怎样? 梅塔先生，我会把我的消息来源带进坟墓
So? Mr. Mehta, I take my sources to my grave.
我只是想弄明白..
I'm just trying to understand...
如果你的线人和我有私人恩怨
...if your source had a personal enmity with me.
他对我有意见吗？
Did he have a problem with me?
“啊? ”
[Harshad] 'Huh?'
每个人都在利用的系统的漏洞进行违规操作
The systemic loopholes and irregularities that everyone was exploiting...
说他们是骗子
...calling them a scam...
也许他利用你来对付我？
...maybe he used you against me..?
利用？
Use?
梅塔先生，我的报告完全基于事实
Mr. Mehta, I report strictly based on facts.
我来这里是因为我认为有必要听听你对这件事的看法
I'm here because I think it's necessary to get your side of the story too.
[苏切塔]“因为我相信你也需要一个公平的听证会”
[Sucheta] 'Because I believe you need a fair hearing too.'
公平的听证会？
Fair hearing?
你的线人告诉了你一些事情..
Your source told you something then...
你相信了，并报道了出来
...you believed it and printed it.
现在，当全世界都在指责我的时候..
And now, when the whole world is pointing fingers at me...
“ ... ... 当我遇到麻烦的时候... ... 现在你又说什么公平听证会? ”
[Harshad] '...when I'm in trouble... Now you talk about a fair hearing?'
我那时就想采访你，但你拒绝了
I tried talking to you even then. But you were in denial.
那时候，你可能觉得没有人可以碰你
Back then, you probably felt that no one can touch you.
你说的这些关于公平和不公平的事情
These things you say... about being fair and unfair...
你以为我不明白你的意思吗？
...do you think I don't understand what you mean?
谈到一个人的利益，没有什么是公平或不公平的
When it comes to one's gain, nothing is fair or unfair.
你知道，在商界，创造财富需要时机
You see, in business, it takes time to create fortune...
毁灭财富也需要时机
...and timing to kill it.
在你的新闻行业，这是一样的，不是吗? 这都是关于时机
In your business of journalism, it is the same, isn't it? It's all about timing.
你和你的线人时机掌握得很好
You and your source timed it very well.
梅塔先生，我不是做新闻的
Mr. Mehta, I am not in the business of journalism.
我根据事实写报道
I write stories based on facts.
重要的报道
Stories that are important. Stories that matter.
这对谁很重要？
Whom do they matter to?
司法系统? 公众? 体制？
The judiciary? The public? The system?
这对任何人来说都不重要
It doesn't matter to anyone.
- 没人在乎-我在乎
- Nobody gives a f**k. - I give a f**k.
由于这种明目张胆的误用和傲慢..
Because of this blatant misuse and blatant arrogance...
整个系统都是狗屁
...the whole system is f****d.
- 你好像被冒犯了...-梅塔先生，我们没什么好说的了
- You seem offended... - Mr. Mehta, I think we are done.
我听说你在写一本关于这个”骗局”的书” ？
I hear, that you're writing a book on this "scam"?
出版前一定要给我看看
Do show it to me before you publish it.
我来交叉核对一下
I'll do a fact-check.
[德巴西]“终于! ”
[Debashis] 'Finally!'
完成了校对
Done with this proofreading.
有时候我觉得，我们应该采纳哈沙德的建议
Sometimes I feel, we should've taken Harshad's suggestion.
他本可以帮忙的
He could've helped.
所有这些数字..
All these numbers and figures...
只是交叉核对一下，就会让人感到困惑
Just cross-checking them can leave one confused.
那我们还要在致谢中提到他的名字
And then, we would have to name him in the acknowledgements too.
哦，是的
Oh yes.
- 这提醒了我...-嗯..
- That reminds me... -[Sucheta] 'Hmm...'
我们还要感谢卡拉姆昌德
We'll have to thank 'Karamchand' too.
你能不能别再叫我的线人“卡拉姆昌德”了？
Can you stop calling my source 'Karamchand'?
- 你知道我叫他 DT-哦，对，深喉
- You know I call him DT. - Oh, yes. Deep Throat. Yeah...
你本可以想出一些原创的东西
You could've come up with something original.
[ Debashis ]“你刚从《总统的手下》里偷来的”
[Debashis] 'You just stole it from All the President's Men.'
你觉得这很有创意吗？
So, you think that is original, huh?
顺便告诉你，他们也获取了你的信息
They also stole it, for your information.
你什么都不知道，去做些调查吧
You don't know anything. Please go and do some research.
我会的
I will.
但我不需要给你的线人打电话
But I don't need to call your source DT...
因为我知道他的真名
...because I know his real name.
- 真的?-当然
- Really? - Of course.
你们两个见过几次面
A couple of meetings between you both...
我就知道”深喉”是谁了
...and I had figured who this "Deep Throat" is...
- 是的... 我知道...-你不相信我
- Yeah... I know... -[Debashis] 'You don't believe me?'
没有
No.
我可以马上告诉你他的名字
I can tell you his name right away.
- 你能吗?-是的
- Can you? - Yes.
- 告诉我-如果我告诉你呢？
- Tell me. - What if I tell you?
- 什么?-我能得到什么回报？
- What? - What do I get in return?
回报? 你是个记者
Return? You're a journalist.
从什么时候开始记者开始考虑收益了？
Since when did the journalists start thinking about returns?
拜托! 总该有点奖励吧
Come on! There has to be some reward.
尽管我知道你消息来源的名字，但我一直对此保持沉默
I kept mum all this while in spite of knowing your source's name.
好吧
Okay. Fine.
你想要什么？
What do you want?
- 用指甲花把你的手装饰好-Debu 拜托..
- With henna, keep your hands decorated - Debu, please...
用鲜花，把轿子装饰起来
With flowers, keep the palanquin decorated
天啊 Debu
Oh, my God, Debu.
为了带你走，美丽的少女，你的爱人将踏上这段旅程！
To take you away fair maiden, your beloved will make this journey!
你要干嘛？
Is there a point to this?
死生契阔，与子成说执子之手，与子偕老
Marry me.
先告诉我消息来源的名字
Tell me the name of my source, first.
你的消息来源帮了大忙
Your source has helped so much.
我们必须在书中感谢他，不是吗？
We have to thank him in the book, don't we?
36. Anil Khurana 先生
Number 36. Mr. Anil Khurana.
下一辆车
[Auctioneer] 'Next car.'
20. Raja Duggal 先生
Number 20. Mr. Raja Duggal.
我作为首相的职责……
...My duties as Prime Minister...
1996年，哈尔沙德再次走运
[Sucheta] 'In 1996, Harshad had a stroke of luck once again.'
拉奥总理辞去了总理职位
'Prime Minister Rao was relinquishing his seat'.
哈尔沙德不再被视为政府的头号敌人... ..
'Harshad was no longer perceived as government's enemy number one...'
“他在一些案件中也得到了和解”
'He had also got relief in a few cases.'
他的头脑又开始工作了
'His mind was at work again.'
五年前我们扬言要摧毁美林
Five years ago we were to destroy Merill Lynch...
一路走来，我们却被摧毁了
Along the way, we got destroyed.
72宗刑事案件
Seventy-two criminal cases.
还有600多起民事案件
And more than 600 civil cases.
我比黑社会的老大指控还多
I'm bigger than a don of the underworld.
不过，是的... ... 这可能会让我进入吉尼斯世界纪录
[Harshad] 'But yes... This might put me in the Guinness Book of World Records.'
别笑，这是事实，不是玩笑
Don't laugh. This is a fact. It's not a joke.
你真是太棒了
And you are amazing.
当我情况不好的时候
When the going got tough...
嘿，白痴！
Hey, idiot!
因为你，中央调查局，IT... ... 他们使我的生活很悲惨
Because of you, CBI, IT... ...they had made my life miserable.
我甚至不能安静地做爱
I wasn't allowed to even s**t in peace.
“我知道如何保持低调”
[Pranav] 'I know how to keep a low profile.'
这就是为什么我很好，我很开心
That is why I'm fine. I'm happy.
但是你..
But you...
你就是巴昌
You are Bachchan.
新人已经进入了宝莱坞和市场
New people have entered Bollywood and the market.
现在，阿米塔布·巴沙坎和哈尔沙德 · 梅塔的时代已经结束了
Now the era of both, Amitabh Bachchan and Harshad Mehta, is over.
亲爱的..
Darling...
时间不会白白流逝
...time doesn't go anywhere.
相反，时间能给你经验
Rather, it brings with it. Experience.
经验有它自己的价值，明白吗？
And experience has its own value. Get it?
没错，经验是有价值的
True. Experience does have value.
这就是我打算写一个报纸专栏的原因
That's why I'm planning to write a newspaper column.
关于市场
About the market.
我会告诉人们买什么，什么时候卖
What to buy, when to sell, I'll advise people.
进来
-[knock on the door] - Come in.
这是什么？
What is this?
这是哈尔沙德 · 梅塔办公室发来的
[Peon] 'This is from Harshad Mehta's office.'
送货员说你会知道的
'The delivery boy said you'll know, that this is for you.'
- 好的，谢谢-好的
- Okay, thank you. -[Peon] 'Okay.'
- 喂?-你拿到照片了吗，苏切塔？
- Hello? - Did you get the photographs, Sucheta ji?
梅塔先生，如果有关于你的文章..
Mr. Mehta, if there's an article about you...
我有很多你的照片
...then I have many pictures of you.
我不知道你为什么要寄照片给我
I don't know why you're sending me all of this.
我怎么敢对我的老板指指点点呢？
How can I tell my boss what to do?
什么？
What?
看起来好像没人告诉你
[Harshad] 'Looks like nobody has told you anything.'
好吧，我告诉你
Fine, I'll tell you.
你将成为我的老板
You're going to be my boss.
[哈沙德]‘从下个月开始，我将在你们报纸上写一篇专栏文章’
[Harshad] 'From next month, I am writing a column in your newspaper.'
既然你是财经版的编辑
And since you're the editor of the finance section...
’ ... 那你就是我的老板了，对吧? ’
'...that makes you my boss, right?'
所以，我想，让我的老板选择
So, I thought, let my boss select the photograph...
“专栏的照片..”
[Harshad] '...that will go with the column.'
(哈沙德)“我写这个专栏不是为了消磨时间”
[Harshad] 'I'm not writing this column just to pass time.'
这是一种保持在公众视野中的策略
This is a strategy to remain in the public eye.
一个人们应该永远谈论的话题
One should always remain a topic of conversation.
欢迎，奈尔先生
Welcome, Mr. Nair.
- 早上好-早上好
- Hello, good morning. - Good morning.
- 请坐-谢谢
- Sit. - Thank you.
阿什温，这是奈尔先生
Ashwin, meet Mr. Nair.
高级传媒经理
Senior media manager.
他在帮我申请《印度时报》的专栏
He's helping me get the column at Times of India.
长官，有个问题
Sir, there's a problem.
高层对你的专栏有些意见
Top management has some issues with your column.
他们不确定是否要马上出版
They are not sure whether they want to publish it right away or not.
你是说苏切塔对我的专栏有意见
You mean Sucheta Dalal has a problem with my column.
但是，先生，我们找到了一个解决办法
But sir, we've found a solution.
有一家印度报纸 Navdesh Samachar..
There's a Hindi newspaper Navdesh Samachar...
他们准备出版你的专栏
...they are ready to publish your column.
[奈尔]“还能扩大投资者的影响范围”
[Nair] 'It also has wider reach among your investors.'
“多数是散户”
'Mostly, the smaller ones.'
“梅塔先生... ”
"Mr. Mehta..."
” ... 有人说你的巅峰时期已经过去了... ”
"...some people say that your best days are behind you..."
” ... 而还有一些人仍然视你为市场领袖”
"...while others look up at you as the market guru."
“这背后的秘密是什么? ”
"What is the secret behind this?"
“没有什么秘密”
"There is no secret."
“完全是实践经验”
"It's all about practical experiences."
“我接触过多种业务”
"I've had this exposure of multiple businesses."
“我很幸运，曾在股市工作过”
"And I am fortunate enough to have worked on the floors of stock market."
“我曾涉足股票市场和货币市场”
"I have dabbled both in stock markets and money markets."
“我敢肯定，没有哪个 MBA 或商界人士有过类似的经历”
"And I'm sure, no MBA or businessmen would have similar experience."
“所以，我的建议比书呆子的建议更实际”
"So, my advice are more practical than bookish."
“有人想要投资... ... ”
"Somebody wants to invest some money today..."
“他可以投资哪些股票... ... ”
"What would be the stocks he is likely to invest in..."
” ... 或者说他应该投资哪些股? ”
"...or he should invest in?"
“市场上有很多股票”
"There are lots of stocks."
“我已经看中了其中的一些”
"I have identified a few of those."
“你愿意为我们指出其中的五支股吗? ”
"Would you like to identify five of them for us?"
“从长远来看会给投资者带来好处的 ”
"The five stocks..."
” ...五只股票 ”
"...that in the long term will yield dividends to its investors."
- ”你会怎么选? ”-”南迪先生... ”
- "Which would you choose?" - "Mr. Nandy..."
“你不能这么轻易地从我嘴里套出那些名字”
"You can't get those names out of me so easily."
“你必须为此付出代价”
[Harshad] "You have to pay the price for it."
[电视评论员]“什么代价? ”
[TV Pundit] "And What is that price?"
“股票”
"The stock itself."
“听着，我知道很多人对我的预测感兴趣... ... ”
[Harshad] "Look, I know many people are interested in my predictions..."
什么也不做，却仍然看起来很忙
Do nothing, and still look busy.
“所以，这就是我所做的”
[Harshad] "So, here is what I've done."
这就是他想做的一切
This all that he wants to do.
“我们在互联网上创建了一个网站”
[Harshad] "We have created a website on the internet."
- 免费提供荐股服务-“ www.Harshad.com”
- Doling out free advice. -[Harshad] "www.harshad.com"
“我会随时更新... ... ”
[Harshad]"I'll keep you posted there..."
(哈萨德)“ ... ... 关于投资的地点和时机”
[Harshad]"...about where to invest and when to invest."
先生，这些孩子是你的未来，对吗？
Dhananjay ji, these boys are your future, right?
是的
Yes.
同样，这也是市场的未来
...in the same way, this is the market's future.
至于情报，没有必要跑去交易所
Now for tips, there's no need to go to the market and...
喝不完的茶，吃不完的三明治
...have endless cups of tea and sandwiches.
有了这台电脑，你可以从家里得到情报，也可以交易
With this computer, you can get tips and also trade, from home.
你明白了吗？
Did you understand?
哈沙德兄弟
Harshad Bhai...
你的大脑里有望远镜吗？
...do you have a telescope attached to your brain?
“你怎么能预见未来? ”
[Broker 1] 'How do you see so far into the future?'
市场真的很想你
The market really misses you.
这次只要震撼市场就行了
Just rock the market this time.
听着，伙计，我见过最糟糕的情况
Look, buddy, I've seen the worst.
所有的账户都被冻结
All the accounts are suspended.
我们不知道在这些案例中会有什么惊喜等着我们
We don't know what surprises are awaiting in these cases.
但是我对未来有一些计划
But I have some plans for the future.
哈沙德以高摩的名义做生意..
Harshad Bhai, doing business in the name of Growmore...
我的意思是，我们没有问题..
I mean, we have no problem...
不要误解我的意思，但是在市场上... 你知道..？
...Don't misunderstand me, but in the market... you know..?
我们... 我们该怎么做？
How... how will we do it?
听着伙计
Look, buddy.
问题是名字，对吧? 所以我们要改名字
The problem is the name, right? So we'll change the name.
但前提是我们想要增长更多
But only if we want to grow more.
是的，购买 Videocon 的股票
[Harshad] 'Yes, buy the shares of Videocon.'
你可以在加尔各答买到
You can buy them from Calcutta.
“伙计，给它一点信心”
[Harshad] 'Buddy, give it some string.'
“方向正确”
'The wind is blowing in the right direction.'
这次会像风筝一样保持高度稳定
This needs to remain high like a kite. Steady.
好
Okay.
进来吧
Come in.
什么事，布尚？
Do you need something, Bhushan?
怎么? 我打扰你了吗？
Why? Did I disturb you?
我要和你谈谈
I need to talk to you.
每个人都盯着我们
Everyone has a hawk's eye on us.
我们已经交易很久了
We're trading after a long time.
你在抬高 BPL 和 Sterlite 的股价
[Bhushan] 'You're pushing up the prices of BPL and Sterlite.'
如果有人怀疑..
If someone even suspects...
我们犯了一个错误，对吗？
We had made a mistake, right?
因此，我正在从这些错误中吸取教训
[Harshad] 'So, I'm moving forward learning from those mistakes.'
我只做我能承受的交易
I will only take it as high as I can handle.
但是如果事情突然发生变化，我该怎么办？
But if something changes out of the blue, what can I do?
“15时45分，印度在Pokhran 范围内进行了... ... ”
"At 15:45 hours, India conducted..."
“ ... 三次地下核试验”
"...three underground nuclear tests in the Pokhran range."
[苏切塔]“在哈尔沙德的杠杆地位达到顶峰时... ... ”
[Sucheta] 'At the peak of Harshad's leveraged position...'
印度在1998年6月进行了一次核试验
'...India conducted a nuclear test in June 1998.'
外国投资者惊慌失措，撤出资金，市场完全崩溃
'Foreigners panicked, pulled out money and the market simply melted.'
- 喂?-嗨
- Hello? - Hi.
你还记得吗，我跟你说过股票的事..
Do you remember, I was telling you about the stocks...
... 斯特莱特，BPL 和维多康，他们的价格是如何飙升的？
...of Sterlite, BPL and Videocon and how their prices were shooting up?
- [ DT ]‘ Hmm. ’-那么，他们所有的价格..
-[DT] 'Hmm.' - So, all of their prices...
在市场下跌后大幅下跌
...drastically fell after the market sank.
[ DT ]“我知道”
[DT] 'I know.'
那么，现在，有消息称是..
So, now, the rumours are...
有一些 Damayanti 集团的公司..
...that there are some Damayanti group of companies...
在操纵价格
...that were rigging their prices.
现在他们在交易所有一笔巨大的违约金
And now they have a huge payment default at BSE.
好吧，那又怎样
[DT] 'Okay, so?'
我发现不是强迫他们付钱
So, I found out that instead of forcing them to pay up...
交易所的人实际上是在帮助他们
...the people at BSE are actually helping them.
我的意思是，他们降低了控制的以股代息的利润
I mean, they've lowered the margins in the scrips they control...
并且正在扭转其他公司以弥补其拖欠款项的情况
...and they are arm-twisting other companies to cover their payment default.
难以置信，为什么疯牛病会允许这样的事情发生？
Unbelievable. Why is BSE even allowing any of this?
对于一些闻所未闻的公司来说，这也是如此
That too, for some unheard-of company.
跟我想的一模一样，所以我做了些调查
Exactly what I thought. So, I did some digging.
然而，看起来交易所正在接受我们的老朋友的指示
And, looks like BSE is taking instructions from our old friend.
谁? 哈沙德？
Who? Harshad?
还有谁? 交易所有一半的人仍然是他的信徒
Who else? Half the people at BSE are still his devotees.
他们在半夜偷偷开市
They opened the trading system in the middle of the night...
以与当天交易完全不符的价格
...to insert synchronised trades at prices...
进行同步交易
...that were completely out of line with the day's trading.
但是为什么哈萨德要去拯救这个 Damayanti 集团？
But why is Harshad trying to bail out this Damayanti group?
我不知道，哈沙德和高摩
I don't know. Harshad and Growmore...
似乎和这些股票没有任何关系
...don't seem to have any connection to these stocks.
- 除非-除非
- Unless... - Unless...
Damayanti 集团和哈沙德有某种联系
...Damayanti Group is in some way connected to Harshad.
没错
Exactly.
你想让我做什么？
What do you want from me?
我们要找出这个 Damayanti 集团的所有细节
We have to pull out all the details of this Damayanti Group.
你能帮我吗？
Can you help me?
所有 Damayanti 集团的公司都是相同的注册地址
All the Damayanti Group of companies have the same address.
1208 Maker Chambers 5，Nariman Point，400021.
It's 1208 Maker Chambers 5, Nariman Point, 400021.
高摩资产管理有限公司？
Growmore Research and Asset Management Limited?
没错
Thank you. Exactly.
而这四个人..
And these four people...
迪利普 · 沙阿、维诺德 · 沙阿、阿尼尔 · 多希和迪尼什 · 多希
...Dilip Shah, Vinod Shah, Anil Doshi and Dinesh Doshi...
是这个 Damayanti 集团的董事
...are directors of this Damayanti group...
各种各样的排列组合
...in various permutations and combinations.
好吧
Okay...
你知道他们是谁吗？
Do you know who they are?
乔蒂 · 梅塔的兄弟们
Jyoti Mehta's brothers.
乔蒂是哈沙德的妻子？
Jyoti is Harshad's wife?
这个歹徒以他岳父岳母的名义开办了一家公司
The outlaw has started a company in the name of his in-laws.
没错，我们终于有证据证明哈沙德和 Damayanti 集团有关
Exactly. We finally have evidence linking Harshad to Damayanti.
怎么样？
You know what?
让我们把这些都交给 SEBI
Let's just give all of this to SEBI.
与上次不同，这次不再是纸老虎
Unlike last time, they are no longer toothless tigers.
我们有证据
They have all the powers.
让他们去调查吧
Let them investigate.
好
Okay.
2月27日，谁从孟买来到了德里？
Who had travelled from Mumbai to Delhi on 27th February?
哈尔沙德 · 梅塔？
Harshad Mehta?
不，先生，是我们的一个员工
[Accountant] 'No, sir. It was one of our employees.'
你看，票是用他的名字订的
Look, the ticket has been booked in his name.
打电话给航空公司确认一下..
Just call up the airline and confirm...
哈尔沙德 · 梅塔是不是在这一天去了德里
...if Harshad Mehta travelled to Delhi on this date.
好的，先生
Sure, sir.
这个号码接到了很多电话
[SEBI Official 2] 'Many calls have been made to this number.'
而且，很多是从同一个号码打来的
And, many calls have also been received from the same number.
- 这是谁的号码?-先生，我不知道
- Whose number is this? - Sir, I don't know.
先生，这是所有的合同条款
Sir, here are all the contract notes.
BPL，录像机，小心保管资料
BPL, Videocon, Sterlite. Keep it carefully.
好的，先生
Sure, sir.
[ Sucheta ]“ Damayanti 集团是由哈尔沙德建立的，这是公认的事实”
[Sucheta] 'It was established that Damayanti Group was set up by Harshad.'
甚至没有人试图掩盖他们的踪迹
'No one even tried to cover their tracks.'
通过垄断股票和操纵价格... ..
'By cornering of shares and price manipulation...'
他们创造了一个人工市场，最终却崩溃了
'...they created an artificial market which ultimately crashed.'
你怎么还没准备好？
How come you aren't ready yet?
你今天不是要去拿你的电视录像吗？
Don't you have to go for your TV recording today?
最近几天不会有录音
There won't be any recording for a few days.
发生了这么多事情... 看起来不妙..
With all the things going on... It won't look good...
没关系
That is fine.
但是你今天甚至都没有锻炼
But you didn't even exercise today.
医生建议你每天锻炼身体
The doctor has advised you to exercise every day.
然后呢？
Then?
来吧
Come on.
跑一会儿
Run a little.
我已经跑了很多年了
I've been running for years now.
现在仍然在跑
Look, I'm still running.
我累了
I'm tired now.
只想休息
I just want to rest now.
我需要平静
I need some peace.
想要平静，首先让头脑冷静
For peace, you need to first calm your mind.
你想得太多了
You think too much.
停止思考
Stop thinking.
一切都会好起来的
Then everything will be fine.
还有..
And...
顺便说一句
By the way...
如果你想要平静，你可以一直想着我
...if you want peace, you can always think about me.
好吧，我试试
Okay, let's try that.
不管怎样..
Anyway...
我现在无处可去
I have nowhere to go now.
没必要去任何地方，留在这里... 和我在一起
There's no need to go anywhere. Stay here... with me.
我可能时日无多了
My time might be up, anytime now.
“我可能不得不去... ... 很快... ... ”
[Harshad] 'And I might have to go... soon...'
你为什么说这些可怕的倒霉话？
Why are you saying such scary jinxed things?
你还跟别人说要永远保持积极的态度
You advise everyone else to always think positive.
我开玩笑的
I'm just joking.
看着我..
Look at me...
我会怎么样？
What's going to happen to me?
-给我泡点茶-不，我不去
- Come on, make some tea for me. - No, I won't.
在我出事之前赶快泡点茶
Quickly make some tea before something happens to me.
我不会丢下你一个人的
I'm not leaving you alone.
你穿戴整齐，好像今天要录节目似的
You're all dressed up, as if you were going to be recorded today.
好看吗？
Is it nice?
‘布尚? ’
[Ashwin] 'Bhushan?'
- 你要走了吗?-是的，我没什么工作，所以..
- Are you leaving? - Yes. I didn't have much work, so...
怎么? 发生什么事了？
Why? What happened?
管理员已经把报告送来了
The custodian has sent the report.
- 报告?-是的
- Report? - Yes.
那个定期的..
The one which comes periodically...
- ... 关于负债和资产的报告?-哦... 是的..
- ...about liabilities and assets? - Oh... Yes...
有很多股票都不见了
An entire lot of shares is missing, Bhushan.
我这里有记录，但不在他们的报告里
I mean, it's in my records but not in their reports.
他们一定是在审计的时候漏掉了
They must've messed it up during the audit.
我再看看那些报告
I'll look into those reports again.
将近270万股股票不见了
Almost 27 lakh shares are missing.
大约价值30亿卢比
Approximately worth 300 crores.
你看
Here...
看看这个..
Look at this...
你以前有没有遇到过这个错误？
Did you come across this mistake before?
兄弟，你们有有价值200亿的资产..
Ashwin Bhai, there are assets worth 2,000 crores...
还有价值1600亿卢比的债务
...and liabilities worth 16,000 crores.
天知道，有多少公司的股票
And god knows, how many shares of how many companies.
光是保存记录就让我头脑发热
Just maintaining the records curdles my brain.
你也看到了他们是怎样把股份存放在储藏室里的
And you have seen how they keep the shares in the custodian's storeroom.
我希望他们没有弄丢那些股票
I hope they haven't misplaced those shares.
放错地方了？
Misplace?
不过别担心，阿什温大哥，我会再查一遍所有的记录
But don't worry, Ashwin Bhai. I'll check all the records again.
我可以走了吗？
May I go?
你赶时间吗？
Are you in a hurry?
不... 你需要的话我就留下来
No... We'll leave together if you say.
去吧
Go.
再见
See you.
“270万股股票怎么会从记录中消失? ”
[Harshad] 'How can 27 lakh shares go missing from the records?'
- 你的数字从来没有错过-没错
- Your figures are never wrong. - No, they aren't.
但是你知道，布尚保存着所有资产的记录
But you know. Bhushan maintains the records of all the assets.
他负责检查管理员的所有报告
He is the one who checks all the reports of the custodian.
但我认为，随着年龄的增长，他脑子已经不太好使了
But I think, with age, his brain has stopped working.
“我不知道他在想什么”
[Ashwin] 'I don't know what goes on his mind.'
谢天谢地，我检查了旧的记录，发现了这个错误
Thankfully, I checked the old records and spotted this mistake.
兄弟，我们必须尽快通知托管人
Bhai, we must inform the custodian as soon as possible.
不，等等..
No, wait...
那个疯子
He's crazy.
他反而会怀疑我们
He'll suspect us instead.
我们再问问布尚，让他再检查一遍
Let's ask Bhushan. Let him check them again.
兄弟，你们不懂法律
Bhai, Bhushan and you don't understand the law.
在监护人之前的报告中
In none of the previous reports from the custodian...
没有这些股票的记录
...are these shares mentioned.
但是，他们在我们的记录中有
But, they're showing in our records.
我亲自检查过了
I've checked them myself.
我觉得是92年
I feel, in '92, when we were both in custody...
我们都被拘留的时候就搞错了
...that's when this mistake has occurred in the records.
[阿什温]“我觉得我们应该明天去，然后汇报一下情况”
[Ashwin] 'I feel we should go tomorrow, and complain about this.'
30亿，兄弟
It's 300 crores, Bhai.
如果我们不早点去找他
If we delay even a little...
即使可能是他们审计过程中出现的错误
...the custodian might blame this back on us.
管理员还是可能会把责任推到我们身上
[Ashwin] 'Even if the problem might be in their records.'
如果我们能找到这270万股..
If we find these 27 lakh shares...
我们的债务将减少30亿卢比
...our liability will be reduced by 300 crores.
- 30亿卢比?-是的
- Three hundred crores? -[Ashwin] 'Yes.'
好吧
Okay.
-说吧-我们只有一个请求
- Tell me. - We have just one request.
请找出所有这些股票..
Please locate all these shares...
... 以我们的名义恢复它们，还有所有的利润
...and restore them in our names, with all the benefits.
首先告诉我，我们谈论的是哪些股票？
First tell me, which shares are we talking about?
他们是怎么消失的？
And how did they go missing?
在1992年，这个案子中..
In 1992, during the case...
法庭扣押了我们所有的财产
...the court had attached all our assets.
有两到三间储藏室，里面装满了股票
There were two to three storerooms full of shares.
其中有270万股
And among them, were these 27 lakh shares.
两到三间储藏室？
Two to three storerooms?
两三个装满股票的储藏室怎么会被托管人弄丢呢？
How can two-three storerooms full of shares be misplaced by the custodian?
你想说什么？
What are you trying to say?
我们偷走了自己的股份？
That we've stolen our own attached shares?
- 你是这个意思，对吧?-请冷静
- That's what you mean, right? -[Custodian] 'Please calm down.'
我们会调查的
We'll do an investigation.
无论如何，你的记录是独一无二的
'Your record is unique, anyway.'
正在进行很多同步调查
There are so many on-going investigations.
再多一项又如何？
What's one more?
怎么了，兄弟？
What is it, Bhai?
你又做了什么？
What have you done now?
我们做了什么？
What did we do?
为什么中央调查局要审问我？
Why does the CBI want to interrogate me?
他们为什么又打电话给我？
Why did they call me again?
没什么，冷静点
It's nothing. Calm down.
我们和托管人谈了丢失股票的事
We spoke to the custodian about those missing shares.
肯定是有警察和调查局的人说了
That a*****e must've told the CBI.
[哈沙德]“所以现在，中央调查局正在进行调查”
[Harshad] 'So now, CBI is enquiring.'
或者是在假装询问
'Or they are pretending to enquire.'
没什么大不了的
It's not a big deal.
他们会询问一些员工仅此而已
They'll question a few employees. That's it.
就这样？
That's it?
你去找管理员之前应该先跟我说一声
You should've spoken to me before going to the custodian.
“跟你说一声? ”
[Ashwin] 'Spoken to you?'
什么意思？
Meaning?
阿什温兄弟，如果 CBI 找我麻烦那么..
Ashwin Bhai, if CBI troubles me, then...
“嘿! ”
[Harshad] 'Hey!'
坐下来，冷静点
Sit down and speak calmly.
- 坐下!-我不想坐！
- Sit! - I don't want to sit!
那就说吧
Then talk.
股票没丢
The shares aren't missing.
“你是什么意思? ”
[Harshad] 'What do you mean?'
我卖掉了那些股票
I sold those shares.
你把它们卖了！
You sold them!
这些股份是法院附加的财产
Those shares were attached by the court.
什么叫你把它们卖了
[Ashwin] 'What do you mean you sold them?'
你把脑子也卖了吗? ！
Have you sold your brain too?!
法院从来没有附加这些股份
The court never attached those shares.
当我出具资产清单时，我根本没有包括这些股票
When I gave the list of assets, I didn't include those shares at all.
然后就像我们经常做的那样，我转移了所有的股份..
Then as we have often done, I transferred all those shares...
卖给一家幌子公司，然后在市场上卖掉
...to a front company and sold them off at the open market.
混蛋！
A*****e!
这是你爹的股份吗！
Were they your father's shares, m**********r!
你怎么能这样对待我们？
How can you f**k us over being one of us?
[ Bhushan ]“我... ? ”
[Bhushan] 'I..?'
“我这样对待你们? ”
'I f****d you over?'
“我他妈这样对待你们? ! ”
'I f****d you over?!'
我他妈的一直在贴你的冷屁股！
All this while I've been kissing your a**!
中央调查局的人在我脸上撒尿的时候，你做什么了？
CBI was pissing on my face. What did you expect me to do?
你有这么多的资产
You have so many assets and properties.
我有什么?
What do I have? An empty drum!
当你得不到保释的时候，感觉就像是世界末日
When you were not getting bail, it felt like the end.
我也有家庭
I also have a family.
我必须为他们着想
I have to think about them.
所以我卖掉了所有的股票
So, I sold off all those shares.
不管价值多少，我都保留了下来
Whatever amount I got, I kept.
[阿什温]“我们那么信任你! ”
[Ashwin] 'We trusted you so much!'
我们像兄弟一样信任你
We believed in you like a brother.
就连我也把哈沙德当作兄弟
Even I had taken Harshad for a brother, Ashwin Bhai.
我相信他，加入了高摩资本
I believed in him, and joined Growmore.
你告诉阿什温
Tell Ashwin Bhai...
当你来找我，让我加入高摩资本的时候
...when you came to me with the offer to join Growmore...
... 你是怎么说的，你这个混蛋！
...what did you say, you m**********r!
你还记得吗？还是我来提醒你？
Do you remember or should I remind you?
你跟我说，“我想创造历史”
You told me, "I want to create history. "
“需要100名员工全力以赴... ... ”
"You need 100 employees who will give their 100 percent..."
“ ... ... 那么，我百分之一千确定我将创造历史”
"...then, I'm 1,000 percent sure I'll create history."
“但只有布尚 · 巴特才能成为这100人的指挥官”
"But only Bhushan Bhatt can be the commander of those 100 people."
“我们是老搭档了”
"We are old partners."
“你想要什么我就给你什么，跟我一起干吧”
"You can take whatever you want. Join hands with me."
我与你同在
[Bhushan] 'I joined hands with you.'
哈沙德，你创造了你的历史
Harshad, you created your history.
但我将成为历史
But I was going to be history.
你让我成为公司的合伙人了吗？
Did you make me a partner in the company?
别说合伙人了，你他妈的让我当办公室文员！
Forget partner, you f**king made me an office-clerk!
你有资格成为合伙人吗？
Are you even worthy of being a partner?
你有那个胆量吗？
Do you have the b**ls?
你是个该死的懦夫
You are a f**king coward.
你在哭什么？
And what are you crying about?
你也赚了很多钱啊
You haven't made less money. You too have minted a lot.
听着，布尚，我绝不会因为你再进监狱一次
Look Bhushan, because of your f**k up, I'm not going to go to jail this time.
你是个骗子，中央调查局会认为我又做了一个骗局
You a*****e, CBI will think that I've done another scam.
你以为我想坐牢吗？
Do you think I want to go to jail?
你应该进监狱
You deserve to be in jail.
-中央调查局会逮捕你的 -别用调查局威胁我！
- The CBI will arrest you. - Don't threaten me with CBI!
- 布尚，你个混蛋!-阿什温
- Bhushan, you m**********r! - Ashwin Bhai!
谁会去把这件事告诉调查局？
Who will tell CBI?
你们俩？
The two of you?
梅塔兄弟？
Mehta Brothers?
那句谚语怎么说了？
Ashwin Bhai, what was that?
五十步笑百步？
The pot calling the kettle black..?
你有这么多的幌子公司
You have so many front companies.
你把这么多股份转让给了他们
[Bhushan] 'You have transferred so many shares to them.'
如果加州调查局知道了这件事，对任何人都不会有好结果的，哈沙德
If CBI gets to know, it won't end well for anyone, Harshad.
如果这些股票仍然下落不明，情况会更好
It would have been better if these shares had remained missing.
布尚，我要我的钱
Bhushan, I want my money.
我不会给你的
You won't get it.
明白吗？我绝不会给你
Hmm? You won't get it.
尽你所能
Do what you can.
如果你有勇气去证明..
And if you have the b**ls then prove...
你拥有这些股份，去找法庭说明
...in court that you own these shares and take them back.
滚出去!
Get out! Get out of here!
[Ashwin] 'Get out! M**********r!'
布尚，你这个混蛋! 我还在市场上
Bhushan, you M**********r! I'm still in the market.
我要让你裸体游街示众
I'll have you paraded naked.
该死的！
F*****g b*****d!
先生，我是哈尔沙德公司一名忠诚的员工
Sir, I'm an honest employee in Harshad's company...
我老板叫我做什么我就做什么
...I do what my boss asks me to.
但是你的老板想要回那些从来没有记录在案的股份
But your boss wants those shares back which were never in the record.
你负责处理所有高摩的资产记录，对吧？
You handle the records of all Growmore assets, right?
- 不是吗? 告诉我-是的
- Isn't it? Tell me. - Yes.
那些股票是怎么消失的
Where have those shares disappeared...
为什么高摩和管理员都没有呢？
...if neither Growmore nor the custodian have them?
他们兄弟俩已经在公开市场上秘密卖掉了所有的股票
The brothers have secretly sold all the shares in the open market.
先生，在1992年管理人扣押哈沙德的资产时
Sir, in 1992 when the custodian attached Harshad's assets...
哈沙德根本没有申报这些股票
...Harshad did not declare those stocks.
他出狱后
And after he got out of jail...
他把所有的股份都转到了幌子公司
...he transferred all the shares to front companies.
在1993年到1995年之间
And between 1993 and 1995...
他悄悄把这些股票在市场上卖掉
...he gradually introduced these shares in the market and sold them.
如果真的是这样
When Harshad had not declared those shares...
他为什么要去找管理员？
...why did he go to the custodian?
先生，你了解哈沙德 · 梅塔吧
Sir, you know Harshad Mehta.
他愚弄了所有人，从股票市场到首相
He has fooled everyone, from the share market to the Prime Minister.
这一次，他是想把责任都推到管理员身上，然后逃脱惩罚
This time too, he thought he'll blame it all on the custodian and get away with it.
这是他的新骗局，先生
This is his new scam, sir.
[阿米塔布]“欢迎大家”
[Amitabh] 'I welcome you all.'
欢迎大家收看今天的节目
'I welcome you all to today's episode.'
我是阿米塔布·巴沙坎，你正在收看的是《谁能成为百万富翁》
'I am Amitabh Bachchan and you're watching "Kaun Banega Crorepati".'
谢谢
'Thank you.'
曾经有一段时间，我是市场上的巴沙坎
There was a time when I was the Bachchan of the market.
我曾为普通人赚了几百万
I used to earn millions for the common man.
现在巴沙坎先生正在让普通人成为百万富翁
Now Mr. Bachchan is making common men millionaires.
即使是巴沙坎先生也不得不..
Even Mr. Bachchan had to move...
从大银幕搬到小银幕再次上演
...from the big screen to the small to make a comeback.
如果我们想再次东山再起，我们也应该从小处着手
If we want to make a comeback again, we should also start small.
好了，嫂子，你有什么要说的吗？
There you go. Bhabhi. Do you have anything to say?
小事和大事一样危险
Small is as risky as big.
而风险是..
And risk is...
... 生活的调味品！
...the spice of life!
他不会改变的
He won't change.
你怎么就不明白呢？
Why don't you understand?
我没有卖出任何匿名股票，这都是我的员工干的..
I haven't sold any anonymous shares. This is all my employee's doing...
你们这些白领罪犯，你们以为你们是谁？
You f**king white-collar criminals. Who do you think you are?
你凌驾于这个体系之上吗？
Are you above the system?
你住在大房子里，开着豪华轿车
You live in big houses, drive luxurious cars.
这样你就可以随便利用我们了吗？
Does that give you the power to use us?
你这个混蛋，那么多人因为你而流落街头
You p**p, so many people are on the streets because of you.
那么多人自杀，你这个混蛋！
So many people died, you m**********r!
开始说吧
Start talking.
坦白一切
Confess everything.
告诉我真相
Tell me the truth.
否则，我会杀了你，把你埋在这里
Otherwise, I'll kill you and bury you right here.
开始说吧！
Start talking!
别担心
[Ashwin] 'Don't worry.'
特别法庭曾经因为马鲁蒂案判了你五年，记得吗？
The special court also gave you five years in the Maruti case, remember?
发生什么事了吗？
Did anything happen then?
我们把它上诉到了最高法院，不是吗？
We took it to the Supreme Court, didn't we?
这一次，他们也不能把你关在监狱里太久
This time too, they can't keep you in jail for long.
我出狱的那天..
The day I get out...
我要杀了布尚
...I'll f*****g kill Bhushan.
忘了布尚吧
Forget Bhushan.
我们以后再处理他
We'll handle him later.
听着，兄弟
Listen, Bhai.
我会以你的身体情况为由申请保释
I'll get you bail on health grounds.
好吗？
Okay?
中央调查局没有任何理由，也不能把你关在监狱里太久
And the CBI can't keep you in jail for long, without any reason.
你说话像个真正的律师
You're talking like a real lawyer.
这是药..
This medicine...
保重身体
Take care of your health.
按时吃药
Take your medicine on time.
不要像我们小时候那样冲进马桶
Don't flush it down the toilet like you did when we were kids.
乔蒂要你经常锻炼..
And Jyoti has asked you to exercise regularly...
我会的，我会的
I'll do it, I will.
我走了
I'll leave now.
我很快就会拿到开庭日期
I'll get the date from the court soon.
别担心
Don't worry.
乔蒂..
Jyoti...
给乔蒂打电话..
Call Jyoti...
先生..
Sir...
医生..
Doctor...
乔蒂... 乔蒂！
Jyoti... Jyoti!
[ Sucheta ]“你的家人对这整个情况有什么反应? ”
[Sucheta] 'What's your family's reaction to this entire situation?'
我和我的家人有不同的观点
[Harshad] 'My family and I have different points of view.'
我站在一边，抱着我的雄心和梦想... ..
'I am on one side, with my ambitions and dreams...'
“另一边是我的家人... ... ”
[Harshad] '...and on the other, is my family...'
他总是阻止施展拳脚
'...who always stop me from doing things.'
我们现在应该怎么做? 为什么我们需要这么做？
'What should we do now? Why do we need to do it... how?'
这些案子又给了他们一个新的借口
'And these cases have given them another excuse.'
但是你看，现在我明白他们说的是有道理的
'But you see, now I see a point in whatever they are saying.'
除了几千万卢比，我不需要钱
'Beyond a few crores, I don't need money.'
“我对数字很在行”
'I'm brilliant with numbers.'
“我知道，如果你不能控制你的钱... ..
'And I know, that if you don't control your money...
它很快就会变成一个诅咒
'...it can quickly become a curse.'
它会给你带来负面的影响
'It starts giving you negative impact rather than positive.'
我不想把这毒药传给我儿子
'And I don't want to pass this poison to my son.'
“钱确实可以变成毒药”
'It's true that money can turn into poison.'
不要被幻想所迷惑，不要为自己的身体骄傲！
Don't be deluded by illusions. Don't take pride in the body!
它就像粘土一样脆弱
It's as fragile as clay
不要被幻想所迷惑不要对自己的身体感到骄傲！
Don't be deluded by illusions Don't take pride in the body!
它就像粘土一样脆弱
It's as fragile as clay.
它像泥土一样脆弱，像一滴露珠
It's as fragile as clay, Like a drop of dew
一阵风... 只是一阵风
A blast of wind... Just a little gust
身体会化为尘土
And the body will turn to dust
有一个严厉的国王
There was a stern king
世界闻名
Famed among nations
大象在他的院子里摇摆
Elephants swayed in his court
- 当大象在他的球场上摇摆-[电话铃声]
- When Elephants swayed in his court -[phone ringing]
泥灯没油了
The clay lamp ran out of oil
一阵风... 只是一阵风
A blast of wind... Just a little gust
身体会化为尘土
And the body will turn to dust
[ Sucheta ]骗局发生后，政府针对银行和股市
[Sucheta] After the scam, the government made many rules...
制定了许多规则..
for both banks and the share market...
很多新规定
A lot changed.
然而，什么都没有发生
And yet, nothing did.
就像世界上其他地方一样，聪明的犯罪头脑..
Like anywhere else in the world, ingenious criminal minds...
继续破坏体系，继续进行诈骗
went on to subvert these systems and scams continued...
1992年的骗局使印度市场彻底崩溃
股价急剧下跌，市值蒸发了超过一万亿卢比
尽管1992年设立了一个特别法院，旨在迅速有效地处理案件
但实际上，在28年后的今天，诉讼仍在继续
在经历这场骗局之后，印度的证券和金融体系
对其基本结构进行了快速改革
SEBI(印度证监会)在监督交易所方面被赋予了深远的权力
骗局曝光后，有关部门共向哈尔沙德·梅塔和他的家人
提起超过70项刑事诉讼和超过600项民事诉讼
大多数的刑事案件被撤销了，但多数民事诉讼还在进行
大多数针对主要被告的案件
在2001年哈尔沙德·梅塔去世后都得到了和解
苏切塔·达拉尔在2006年被授予新闻界享有盛誉的Padma Shri
阿什温·梅塔继续作为律师亲自处理所有案件
这个骗局或者说违规行为，随便你怎么称呼..
This whole scam or whatever you call, irregularities...
不是由任何一个人犯下的
...has been not committed by any one person...
或者任何一群人
...or any one group of persons.
而是整个业务
It is the whole business.
令人惊讶的是，我们提供给印度储备银行的证词就在那里
And to the surprise, even now the confession is there from the RBI.
他们从去年就知情... 一年多了
That they were aware of it since last... more than a year.
所以就算是监管机构也无法改变..
So even they couldn't change it...
银行
...banks who were the deciding authority...
才是那个..
...who are the one who had the...
在市场上有发言权的角色
...more of a say in the market.
经纪人只是整个市场的一小部分
Brokers are the small segment of the whole market.
我只有一个请求
Only one and one...
就是..
...my request is...
我不想要花束
...I don't want bouquets.
别在我身上下大赌注
Don't give me big bets.
过山车坐得太刺激了
It's too much of a swing from top to the bottom...
现在跌落神坛，我不会说我是英雄
...and again swinging back up. And I won't say I'm a hero.
让我做我自己，我为我自己感到骄傲，仅此而已
Let me be what I am and I am proud of what I am. That's all.